A Guide to the Office of Institutional Research Records, 1975-1998: UA 0042
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Office of Institutional Research Records,
1975-1998
Special Collections, James Madison University
JMU Office of Institutional Research
UA 0042
.4 cubic feet; 1 box
The Office of Institutional Research Records contains reports, newsletters, surveys and studies, from 1975-1998.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Items were transferred from the Office of Institutional Research in April 1994. One report was transferred from SE 92-0929, Department and Committee Self-Study Reports (now UA 0043) in 2018.
Administrative History
The Office of Institutional Research, originally called the Office of Planning and Analysis, is charged with the following functions: developing, collecting and communicating measures of institutional effectiveness, providing leadership with information and policy analysis; promoting the university's planning process, and compiling and reporting mandated information. Current data can be found on the Office of Institutional Research website: http://www.jmu.edu/oir/index.shtml.
Scope and Content
"Student Development News," originally published in 1978 by the Office of Student Affairs, contains student demographic information, as well surveys assessing such topics as student perceptions of JMU and students' personal values (1:2-3).
The file called "Reports, 1984-1991," contains the following reports completed by the Office of Institutional Research: Cost of Instruction at James Madison University, Academic Years 1975-1976 through 1982-83; Ten Year Summary of Selected OCR Data for Black Undergraduate Students 1975 – 1985; Academic Performance of Transfers from Virginias' Public Two-Year Institutions at James Madison University, May 1989; Report of the Committee to Review Institutional Size, April 1988; Response to the Report of the Commission on the University of the 21st Century, May 1991; and Economic Impact of JMU on the Harrisonburg/Rockingham County area and the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1992 (1:4).
The Office of Planning and Analysis newsletter, "Research Notes," addresses topics such as enrollment, graduation rate, retention, faculty salaries and faculty activities, and transfer students, among others (1:5).
The Virginia Summary Plan Reports appear to be a product of the Office of Student Assessment, and discuss aspects of student assessment, including alumni surveys regarding satisfaction with various aspects of their education, program reviews, discussions of the Liberal Studies and General Education programs, and student demographic information (1:6).
Arrangement
Collection is arranged chronologically.
Related Materials
"Statistical Summary Reports," published annually by the Office of Institutional Research, are cataloged and available in Special Collections. Current years can be found on the OIR website: http://www.jmu.edu/oir/index.shtml.
Index Terms
Subjects:
James Madison University -- Statistics; James Madison University -- Students -- Statistics; Madison College -- Statistics; Madison College -- Students -- Statistics; Education, Higher -- Research; Education, Higher -- United States -- Statistics; Universities and colleges -- Planning
Genre and Form Terms:
Questionnaires; Newsletters; Administrative reports
- JMU Faculty Activity Surveys, 1975-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Student Development News" Newsletter, 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Student Development News" Newsletter, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reports, 1984-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Career Planning and Placement Follow-Up Report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Research Notes" Newsletter, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Virginia Summary Plan Reports Re: Student Assessment, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Faculty Salary Data, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Faculty Salary Surveys, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- General Education Surveys, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)